Guide to the Jesse Hurd Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Jesse Hurd family papers
1700-1910
MS 295
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5.25
(14 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, diaries, legal papers, account books, ship's papers, and miscellanea relating to the private lives and business interests of the Hurd family of Chatham, Connecticut, and New York, New York. Family interests in shipbuilding, ship repair, mercantile holdings, distillery operations, and politics are detailed, with extensive records for the New York Screw Dock Company and for many of the ships built, owned, and operated by the Hurd family.
Hurd, Jesse, approximately 1760-1831
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Margaret S. Dart, 1961, 1965.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Correspondence and Papers, 1774-1853. II. Business Papers, 1700-1910. III. Ship's Papers, 1791-1831.
Scope and Contents
The Jesse Hurd Family Papers consist of correspondence, diaries, legal papers, account books, ship's papers, and miscellanea relating to the private lives and business interests of the Hurd family of Chatham, Connecticut, and New York, New York. Family interests in shipbuilding, ship repair, mercantile holdings, distillery operations, and politics are detailed, with extensive records for the operations of the New York Screw Dock Company and for many of the ships built, owned, and operated by the Hurd family.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Three generations of the Hurd family of Chatham, Connecticut, are represented in the papers. The primary figures are Jesse Hurd (1760-1831); his brother Benjamin Hurd (1739-1781); Jesse's sons Jesse II, Cyrus, and Nelson; and Cyrus Hurd's sons Cyrus II and Charles W.B. Hurd.
Jesse Hurd was a storekeeper, distiller, ship builder, shipmaster, shipowner, state representative from Chatham, and first president of the New York Screw Dock Company (1827-1831).
Nathaniel Lynde Griswold (1773-1866); George Griswold (1776-1859), and Huntington Selden are also represented in the papers, in relation to their business dealings with the Hurd family.
For a chart outlining the genealogical relations of the Hurd family, please consult the Genealogical Chart.
Brazil; Business; Distilling industries -- Connecticut; Families; Shipbuilding -- Connecticut; Shipping -- Connecticut; California -- History -- 1846-1850; Chatham (Conn.); Connecticut -- Politics and government -- 1775-1865; Haddam (Conn.); Docks -- New York (State) -- New York; Wharves -- New York (State) -- New York; United States -- Commerce -- South America; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; United States -- History -- War of 1812; West (U.S.); Account books; Diaries; Ships' papers; Businessmen; Merchants; Public officers; Shipmasters; Griswold, George, 1777-1859; Griswold, Nathaniel Lynde, 1773-1866; Hurd, Benjamin, 1739-1781; Hurd, Benjamin; Hurd, Cyrus; Hurd, Drusilla Dart, b. 1768; Hurd, Jesse, approximately 1760-1831; Hurd, Nelson; Hurd, Norman; Hurd, William A.; Selden, Huntington; Smith, Hezekiah, ca. 1750-1826; Griswold family; Hurd family; United States. Navy -- Pay, allowance, etc.; Bolivar (Brig); New York Screw Dock Company; United States. Army. New York Infantry Regiment, 9th (1861-1863)
- Correspondence and Papers, 1774-1853; Series I; 1 linear foot (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains letters, diaries, legal papers and other materials documenting the activities of family members. Correspondence includes letters relating to the War of 1812, to events in Chatham and Haddam, Connecticut, and to the business pursuits of Jesse Hurd and others. Cyrus Hurd's letters from California (1849-1853) and Charles W.B. Hurd's letters prior to the Civil War battle at Antietam (1861-1862) are also arranged here. Correspondence from South America, Cuba, China, and elsewhere reflect the family's widespread shipping interests. The vagaries of maritime life detailed in letters include ship orders, foreign markets, ship sales, shipwrecks, credit needs, piracy, and financial considerations. Correspondents include: Huntington Selden, Captain Hezekiah Smith, Captain Stephen Griffith, David and Abijah Brainerd, and others.
  Diaries arranged in the collection (box 2) include Jesse Hurd's notes on his years in the Connecticut General Assembly (1808-1809), Cyrus Hurd II's Brazilian voyage (1826-1827), Cyrus Hurd, Sr.'s United States trip to the western frontier (1836), and Charles W.B. Hurd's Civil War diary (1861-1862).
  Arrangement
  This series contains material arranged alphabetically by record type.
  - Correspondence
    - 1803-1846 (Box 1, Folder 1-19)
    - 1848-1883 (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
  - Diaries
    - Hurd, Jesse: Connecticut General Assembly, 1808-1809 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Hurd, Cyrus, II: Brazil voyage, 1826-1827 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Hurd, Cyrus, Sr.: U.S. western trip, 1836 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Hurd, Charles W.B.: Civil War, 1861-1862 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Estate inventories: Hurd, Jesse, 1830-1846 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Legal papers, 1774, 1802-1830 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Papers
    - Brazil trade, 1826-1827 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - China trade, 1835-1839 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Poems: Hurd, Cyrus, II, 1849-1853 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Printed material, 1817-1830 (Box 2, Folder 31-32)
- Business Papers, 1700-1910; Series II; 3 linear feet (8 boxes)
  This series includes information on three areas of Hurd family business dealings. General files contain several account books (boxes 3-5) detailing Jesse Hurd's financial transactions in Chatham, Connecticut, and elsewhere. Bills and receipts (boxes 6-9) provide similar financial information. Distillery files consist of bills relating to the Hurds' business activities in Connecticut, including the purchase of goods to produce liquor. New York Screw Dock Company files include accounts of workers wages and hours, legal papers, and miscellanea relating to the operations of this company. The company owned three docks and the apparatus to remove ships from the water to effect repairs and cleaning. Legal papers note the liquidation of the company stock in 1910.
  This series is arranged in three sections: General, Distillery, and New York Screw Dock Company. Each section is arranged alphabetically by record type.
  - General
    - Account Books
      - 1801-1810 (Box 3, Folder 33-41)
      - 1811-1820 (Box 4, Folder 42-53)
      - 1819-1839 (Box 5, Folder 54-63)
    - Bills and Receipts
      - 1700-1808 (Box 6, Folder 64-75)
      - 1809-1820 (Box 7, Folder 76-87)
      - 1821-1828 (Box 8, Folder 88-97)
      - 1829-1840, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 98-101)
  - Distillery
    - Bills, 1810-1820 (Box 10, Folder 102)
  - New York Screw Dock Company
    - Accounts of worker's wages and hours, 1828-1829 (Box 10, Folder 103-104)
    - Legal Papers, 1827-1910 (Box 10, Folder 105)
    - Miscellaneous Papers, 1825-1833 (Box 10, Folder 106-110)
- Ship's Papers, 1716-1831; Series III; 1.25 linear feet (4 boxes)
  This series contains financial data, construction, cargo, repair and outfitting information for more than seventy-five (75) vessels (ships, brigs, sloops, schooners) that members of the Hurd family owned, operated, sailed, or repaired. Material pertaining to the Bolivar is extensive, with financial records and correspondence with the Griswolds. The diary of Cyrus Hurd II details one of this brig's voyages.
  This series contains files arranged alphabetically by the name of the vessel.
  - Schooner Abcona, 1814-1817 (Box 11, Folder 111)
  - Ship Active, 1812-1813 (Box 11, Folder 112)
  - BrigActress, 1815-1818 (Box 11, Folder 113)
  - Brig Alexander, 1820-1829 (Box 11, Folder 114)
  - Sloop Alfred, 1825-1831 (Box 11, Folder 115)
  - Schooner Alpha, 1828 (Box 11, Folder 116)
  - Sloop Antelope, 1820 (Box 11, Folder 117)
  - Brig Athalia, 1828 (Box 11, Folder 118)
  - Ship Blooming Rose, 1816 (Box 11, Folder 119)
  - Brig Bolivar
    - 1825-1827, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 120-130)
    - 1828-1830, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 131-136)
  - Brig Boxer, 1824-1825 (Box 12, Folder 137)
  - Ship Catharine Ann, 1815 (Box 12, Folder 138)
  - Ship Ceres, 1806-1810 (Box 12, Folder 139)
  - Ship Chancellor, 1823-1824 (Box 12, Folder 140)
  - Ship Charles, 1809 (Box 12, Folder 141)
  - Sloop Cleopatra, 1810-1824 (Box 12, Folder 142)
  - Ship Columbia, 1801-1802 (Box 12, Folder 143)
  - Brig Commerce, 1791 (Box 12, Folder 144)
  - Ship Cornelia, 1810-1815 (Box 12, Folder 145)
  - Ship Cornelia, 1810-1815 (Box 12, Folder 146)
  - Sloop Dart, 1825-1830 (Box 12, Folder 147)
  - Schooner David, 1828 (Box 12, Folder 148)
  - Schooner Delight, 1802 (Box 12, Folder 149)
  - Schooner Durango, 1830-1831 (Box 12, Folder 150)
  - Schooner Eagle, 1804-1823 (Box 13, Folder 151)
  - Sloop Fair Haven, 1831 (Box 13, Folder 152)
  - Sloop Fair Lady, 1816 (Box 13, Folder 153)
  - Brig Fair Play, undated (Box 13, Folder 154)
  - Brig Falcon, 1823 (Box 13, Folder 155)
  - Ship Fortitude, 1810 (Box 13, Folder 156)
  - Ship Fox, 1812-1813 (Box 13, Folder 157)
  - Brig Francis, 1827 (Box 13, Folder 158)
  - Sloop Gertrude, 1824 (Box 13, Folder 159)
  - Brig Gold Searcher, 1797-1808 (Box 13, Folder 160)
  - Sloop Gordon, 1831 (Box 13, Folder 161)
  - Schooner Gypsy, 1815-1816 (Box 13, Folder 162)
  - Ship Helen Mar, 1826-1827 (Box 13, Folder 163)
  - Ship Henry, 1818-1820 (Box 13, Folder 164)
  - Sloop Henry, 1815-1825 (Box 13, Folder 165)
  - Ship Heroine, 1827-1828 (Box 13, Folder 166)
  - Sloop Hetta, 1824 (Box 13, Folder 167)
  - Ship Independence, 1805-1808 (Box 13, Folder 168)
  - Sloop Industry, 1798-1799 (Box 13, Folder 169)
  - Ship James, 1805 (Box 13, Folder 170)
  - Brig James Wells, 1808 (Box 13, Folder 171)
  - Ship John, 1820-1821 (Box 13, Folder 172)
  - Ship John Drew, 1809 (Box 13, Folder 173)
  - Ship John Hagan, 1831 (Box 13, Folder 174)
  - Ship Juliet, 1811-1812 (Box 13, Folder 175)
  - Ship Laura, 1803-1816 (Box 13, Folder 176)
  - Ship Lavinia, 1822-1824 (Box 13, Folder 177)
  - Brig Lewis, 1816 (Box 13, Folder 178)
  - Ship Liberty, 1822-1825 (Box 13, Folder 179)
  - Brig Lambert, 1807 (Box 13, Folder 180)
  - Ship Marion, 1830-1831 (Box 13, Folder 181)
  - Schooner Marlburg, 1806 (Box 13, Folder 182)
  - Schooner Mary, 1803-1831 (Box 13, Folder 183)
  - Sloop Mary, 1830 (Box 13, Folder 184)
  - Schooner Mary Ann, 1813-1818 (Box 13, Folder 185)
  - Ship Mercator, 1817 (Box 13, Folder 186)
  - Ship Mermaid, 1800-1809 (Box 13, Folder 187)
  - Ship Mentor, 1826-1828 (Box 13, Folder 188)
  - Schooner Minerva, 1800-1801 (Box 13, Folder 189)
  - Ship Mirror, 1818 (Box 13, Folder 190)
  - Sloop Nelson, 1824-1826 (Box 14, Folder 191)
  - Neptune's Barge, 1822-1823 (Box 14, Folder 192)
  - Brig Nerimae, undated (Box 14, Folder 193)
  - Brig New Hanover, 1828-1831 (Box 14, Folder 194)
  - Brig North Carolina, 1824-1825 (Box 14, Folder 195)
  - Sloop Nun, 1828-1829 (Box 14, Folder 196)
  - Brig Nymph, 1716-1818 (Box 14, Folder 197)
  - Brig Oliver, 1804 (Box 14, Folder 198)
  - Sloop Olynthus, 1831 (Box 14, Folder 199)
  - Ship Orion, 1804 (Box 14, Folder 200)
  - Sloop Paragon, 1817-1818 (Box 14, Folder 201)
  - Brig Planter, 1820 (Box 14, Folder 202)
  - Brig Polly, 1802 (Box 14, Folder 203)
  - Ship Potosi, 1821, 1825 (Box 14, Folder 204)
  - Ship Pulaski, 1831-1833 (Box 14, Folder 205)
  - Schooner Return, 1813-1815 (Box 14, Folder 206)
  - Ship Robert Wilson, 1824-1828 (Box 14, Folder 207)
  - Sloop Satellite, 1814 (Box 14, Folder 208)
  - Sloop Spark, 1816-1818 (Box 14, Folder 209)
  - Brig Stationer, 1806 (Box 14, Folder 210)
  - Schooner Tamaulipas, 1829-1830 (Box 14, Folder 211)
  - Brig Thetis, 1821-1828 (Box 14, Folder 212)
  - Brig Traveller, 1808-1812 (Box 14, Folder 213)
  - Schooner Triton, 1828 (Box 14, Folder 214)
  - Sloop Triumph, 1831 (Box 14, Folder 215)
  - Brig Trollee, 1814 (Box 14, Folder 216)
  - Sloop Unity, 1816-1821 (Box 14, Folder 217)
  - Brig Venus, 1814-1815 (Box 14, Folder 218)
  - Schooner Viper, 1812-1813 (Box 14, Folder 219)
  - Ship Walter, 1810 (Box 14, Folder 220)
  - Brig Wasp, 1816 (Box 14, Folder 221)
  - Ship William, 1817 (Box 14, Folder 222)
  - Sloop William and Alfred, 1812 (Box 14, Folder 223)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 14, Folder 224-225)